Okay, Boker Tov, today's Daf is ע"ד ed. *Ayin Daled* Bava Kamma
74. We pick up with the last word on ע"ג עמוד ב׳
*Ayin Gimmel Amud Bet*, ממי *Mimai*. We're dealing with a debate of
Abaye and Rava whether הכחשה תחילת הזמה hachashah techilas hazamah. *hachasha techilat
hazama*, whether contradiction is the neutralizing of the testimony is the beginning
of the process of הזמה hazama. *hazama*.
So basically, כת kat א׳ *Kat A* says that Reuven killed somebody
on Monday and כת kat ב׳ *Kat B* first says no, Reuven
was with us on Monday. So they're contradicting A, but in that
case that's not הזמה hazama. *hazama*, so it neutralizes the testimony of
A, and then כת kat ב׳ *Kat B* says actually you עדים
edim *aidim* and you were also with us on Monday, so that's
הזמה hazamah, *hazama*. So do we say that once its the testimony
has been neutralized they can no longer do הזמה hazamah? *hazama* because
now the testimony is no longer live? That is the position of
Abaye, הכחשה hachchasha *hachasha* is is not תחילת הזמה techilas hazamah. *techilat
hazama*. Or do we say that הכחשה hachchasha *hachasha* is the beginning
of a process but ultimately הזמה hazamah *hazama* is the end of
the process and the fact that the testimony has been contradicted is
just the beginning of knocking it down and it doesn't prevent הזמה
hazamah *hazama* from taking place afterwards? That's Rava's position that הכחשה hachchasha
היא תחילת הזמה hazamah. *hachasha hi techilat hazama*. So Rava tries to
prove it from a ברייתא braisa, *braita* that speaks about witnesses that
say that a certain master first knocked out the eye of his
slave and then the tooth, and the master wants them to say
that because it's implicit that there's another testimony out there that it
was first the tooth and then the eye, which would have him
paying the cost of the eye to the slave because the slave
would've gone free with the tooth. So the master would rather the
testimony be the eye and then the tooth and then he only
has to pay the cost of the tooth. And it says that
if they say the eye and the tooth consistent with the master
and then they become זוממים zomemim *zomemim*, so they have to go
ahead and pay the cost of the eye to the master because
that's what they were trying to cheat him out of because the
real testimony was that the eye was second and not the tooth.
Now that only makes sense if we say that there is this
other testimony out there that has it going in the reverse way,
so and has go, you know, first first the tooth and then
the eye. So Rava says that has to be the case, so
you see הכחשה hachchasha. תחילת הזמה hazamah, *hachasha techilat hazama* that the
עדים זוממים edim zomemim. *aidim zomemim* that there was, you know, first
testimony about the the tooth and then the eye, the עדים edim
*aidim* the the one who were proved lying reversed it and said
eye and then the tooth and then they were proven זוממים zomemim
*zomemim*. So it starts with הכחשה hachchasha *hachasha* it ends with הזמה
hazamah. *hazama* and you see that they can be made זוממים zomemim
*zomemim*. And Abaye disagrees and Abaye says no, there was no other
there weren't three groups of עדים edim *aidim*, there was only two.
The first עדים eidim *aidim* said that it was the tooth and
then the eye, excuse me, the eye and then the tooth and
then the second עדים edim *aidim* came and said no, you were
with us, so that's הזמה hazamah. *hazama* before הכחשה hachchasha *hachasha* and
we actually know that it was the reverse and it actually was
the tooth before it actually was the tooth and then the eye.
Okay,
so therefore you don't have to deal with הכחשה hachchasha. תחילת הזמה
hazamah *hachasha techilat hazama* because the one that are מזמימים *mazimim* are
also the one that puts forth the other story, but it is
clear that there has to have been another story being put forth
here. So now Abaye says so let's read that the last line
of ע"ג עמוד ב׳ *Ayin Gimmel Amud Bet*, אמר אביי Amar Abaye,
לא דהפכינון והזמינינון *Amar Abaye lo d'hafchinun v'hazminun*. No, the case is
not that there was another כת kat *kat* of עדים edim *aidim*
that gave a different story but that the עדים edim *aidim* that
did הזמה hazamah. *hazama* were also the ones that reversed the story.
ממי *Mimai*, how do I know that? מדסיפא במפיך והזמה רישא reisha
נמי במפיך והזמה *Mi d'seifa b'mafich v'hazama reisha nami b'mafich v'hazama*. Since
that's the case at the end it's also the case at the
beginning. דתני סיפא seifa. *D'tani seifa*, the end of the ברייתא braisa
*braita* says, מדנו את איש פלוני שהפיל את שן עבדו וסימא את
עינו *midanu es ish ploni she'hipeel es shen avdo v'simei es eino*.
שהרי העבד אומר כן *Sheharei ha'eved omer ken*. This is the reverse,
that כת kat א׳ *Kat A* says something that the עבד eved
*eved* likes, that first it was the tooth and then the eye.
ונמצאו זוממים zomemim *V'nimtzu zomemim* and then they're found זוממים zomemim *zomemim*,
משלמין דמי עין לרב *meshalmin d'mei ayin l'rav*. So then they have
to pay the cost of the eye to the master. Now again
that only makes sense if there's an alternative testimony that it was
the reverse which is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says. היכי דמי
*Heichi dami*, what's the case? אי דלא קמודו להו בתראי בחבלה כלל
*Ee d'lo kamodeh leihu batrai b'chavala klal*, if the second כת kat
*kat*, if the people that made them זוממים zomemim. *zomemim* say, you
know, don't aren't giving an alternative story, they just say the first
כת kat *kat* was totally, you know, lying, they totally, so then
דמי כולי עבד eved. לרב בעי לשלומי ליה *d'mei kulei eved l'rav
baye l'shalumi lei*. So then the first כת kat *kat* was saying
that the slave goes free when that's not true. So they actually
have to pay the entire cost of the slave, right? Because there's
no alternate story. It's just one כת kat *kat* said that it
was tooth and then eye and then they said you're lying. So
then they would have to pay the master for the cost of
the slave and the cost for his eye, the whole thing was
made up. That can't be the case. In both of these cases
the רישא reisha *reisha* and the סיפא seifa *seifa* it's clear that
there was the alternate story that gets established once this כת kat.
*kat* is found זוממים zomemim *zomemim*. אלא פשיטא דקמודו כולי בחבלה *Ella
p'shita d'ka modeh kulei b'chavala*, it must be that everybody agrees to
the חבלה *chavala*, meaning ודהפכינון והזמינינון *v'd'hafchinun v'hazminun* and that it's really
the second כת kat *kat* that reverses it. Now,
so therefore you see that in that case there is a second
but not but not a third כת kat *kat*. Now you might
ask like how do you... You know there's not a third כת
kat maybe there's you know both things take place there's one you
know this כת kat says that there is the the tooth and
then the eye and then another כת kat says the eye and
then the tooth and then there's הזמה. How does אביי Abaye know
that there's only two כתות kitot here? So the reason רש"י Rashi
says is because in this case if there was a כת kat
that had already said the reverse you know the way we wanted
to suggest about the earlier case. If there's a כת kat that
had already said that it was the eye and then the tooth
and then they came and said the tooth and then the eye
so then this כת kat. of עדים edim actually would not have
been making the master obligated to pay the eye because it would
already have been contradicted by the testimony of the tooth. So they're
so they're therefore you would never have a case where the testimony
of the eye would have been something that have would have been
believed from the get-go so there cannot be any payment for הזמה.
Now that's different than the earlier case the earlier case it could
have worked because if the first testimony was was tooth and then
eye and then the next witnesses came and said eye and then
tooth so in that case the second testimony of tooth is believed
because you would now have one testimony that says eye you have
to pay the cost of the eye and one that says tooth
so they can't both be true but you'll do the lesser of
the two because at least that's the overlap. So in that case
when the second group said tooth which was the first case of
the רישא reisha you would have listened to them and therefore that
would have been a case of עדים edim זוממים. zomemim But in
this case where the second כת kat where the כת kat that
becomes זוממים zomemim. is saying eye it has to be that they're
the only ones saying it there can't be a contradiction if there
was a contradiction you never would have accepted their testimony of eye
because that was demanding more payment so it couldn't be that there
was
a פסק psak out there that was contradicting it. Okay so that's
what אביי Abaye says since in this case the testimony of
eye could not have had anybody contradicting it until it became זוממים
zomemim. or else it never would have been accepted it must be
that there was only that second כת kat, and not three כתות
kitot only that second כת kat of זוממים zomemim, and they said
that you were זוממים zomemim. and also it happened in the reverse
okay. So now the גמרא Gemara so that and because that case
is only two כתות kitot you know only two כתות kitot the
first case is also only two כת. kat Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara just figures this out והיכי דמי v'heichi dami what's the
case? אי דקאמרי אחרי אחרי I d'ka'amrei acharei acharei if הני בתראי
hani basrai אכתי דמחייב ליה לרביה שלומי a-kati d'me-eved l'rabya shulmei דכי
מחייב ליה לגברא אכתי גברא לאו בר חיובא הוא. d'chi michayav lei
l'gavra kati gavra lav bar chiyuva hu. So if the second כת
kat says that the when this event happened you know that the
that the slave had his eye knocked out and his tooth knocked
out if they're saying that the reverse version of it happened happened
after your testimony you testified that it happened on Sunday we're saying
that it got knocked out we're saying it happened you're saying first
of all you're lying עמנו הייתם imanu hayisitem and the reverse happened
on Monday. Okay so if the contrary testimony is set to have
taken place after so then so then הני בתראי hani basrai אכתי
דמחייב ליה לרביה שלומי a-kati d'me-eved l'rabya shulmei
so then when they're saying that it happened on Sunday so on
Sunday the master wasn't חייב chayav anything right? It's now so in
that case they're trying to make him pay the full cost of
the עבד eved which he was not obligated to pay until Sunday
because on Sunday nothing had happened the reverse thing happened on Monday
but they said it happened on Sunday דכי מחייב ליה לגברא אכתי
גברא לאו בר חיובא הוא d'chi michayav lei l'gavra kati gavra lav
bar chiyuva hu because when they're saying on Sunday this is what
happened they're making him pay for for a slave whether it's the
eye and the tooth or the tooth and the eye
but the actual event which the later עדים edim, say and we
believe the later עדים edim the actual event happened Monday. So they
were trying to obligate him on something going back to Sunday which
he was not obligated for so they would have to pay the
full cost of the עבד. eved Okay אלא דקמקדמי קדומי ella d'kamiktamei
k'dumei הני בתראי hani basrai
so it must be that they said it happened beforehand the you
know the first כת said that it happened on Sunday eye tooth
tooth eye and then the second כת that makes them זוממים zomemim
says first of all עמנו הייתם imanu hayisitem you're זוממים. zomemim, Second
of all what you're testifying it happened but it happened in the
reverse and it happened on שבת Shabbos it didn't happen on Sunday.
So in that case that's why the כת when they're זוממים zomemim,
doesn't have to pay the full cost of the עבד eved because
what they're saying happened on Sunday when that happened the master was
already חייב chayav to free the עבד because of what he did
on שבת Shabbos and therefore what the second כת is saying is
only the question of eye versus tooth which was later but the
reality of the חיוב chiyuv that existed before. before they claimed that
he was חייב. chayiv. But one more thing we have to clarify.
ואי דלא עמד בדין, V'ee d'lo amad b'din, but if it only
happened on שבת, Shabbos, but there had not yet been a court
case, אכתי דמכלי הוה ליה לרביה לשלומי ליה, achti d'michlei hava lei
lerabei leshalumei lei, then it wouldn't matter that he knocked out his
eye on שבת. Shabbos. When they said that he did it on
Sunday, the master was not yet obligated to free the slave until
there's המרה בדין. hamarah b'din. Since freeing a slave is a קנס,
knas, that חיוב chiyuv does not exist until בית דין beis din
says it does. Either because the master could just be מודה ופטור
modeh u'patur or even bracketing that fact about פטור, patur, the reality
of a קנס knas is the obligation, it's not like a debt.
The obligation is imposed by בית דין. beis din. So therefore, it's
not enough that he knocked out the eye on שבת. Shabbos. He
wasn't yet obligated to free the slave. And when they testified that
he did this act that knocked out the eye or the tooth
or whatever on Sunday, they were making an innocent man or a
man that wasn't obligated, obligated. So therefore, that they should have to
pay the whole cost of the slave. So we have to create
a scenario that what they're testifying happened on Sunday, he not only
did the act that would lead to an obligation in בית דין,
beis din, but he was actually already obligated to free the slave
from beforehand. It was just that the order happened in the reverse.
אלא דעמד בדין. ela d'amad b'din. Okay. So he had to have
an המרה בדין. hamarah b'din. So basically, כת number one says he
knocked out the eye and then the tooth on Sunday or the
reverse, okay, we're dealing with both the רישא reisha and the סיפא.
seifa, כת number two comes and says, first of all, עמנו הייתם,
imanu hayisem, so we don't deal with הכחשה תחלת הזמה hachchasha techilas
hazamah because they're starting with הזמה, there's only the second כת. And
they say what you say happened on Sunday actually happened before Sunday
and there was actually המרה בדין hamarah b'din before Sunday. So therefore,
when you testify what happened on Sunday, you weren't saying a person,
you weren't making him pay a slave he wasn't obligated to free,
he was already obligated to free it, but you were lying about
which order and therefore that has consequences about paying the cost of
the tooth or the cost of the eye. Okay. So that idea
that there was המרה בדין hamarah b'din is sort of independent of
אביי ורבא. Abaye v'Rava. But אביי Abaye says that this second case
to me is clear that there were only two כיתות עדים kitos
eidim and therefore the first case is the same way and there
was no הכחשה hachachasha that came first. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה
דרב איקא לרב אשי. amar lei Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ika l'Rav
Ashi. So רב אחא בריה דרב איקא Rav Acha brei d'Rav Ika
says to רב אשי, Rav Ashi, דוקיא דרבא מהיכא? dukyah d'Rava meheicha?
Where is רבא Rava getting his inference that it is, what do
you, that it is,
getting his inference that הכחשה תחלת הזמה, hachchasha techilas hazamah, that the
first case was three כיתות עדים kitos eidim and that there was
already a הכחשה hachachasha. before the
הזמה? דוקיא דרבא מהיכא אילימא מרישא רישא כי מיתכחשי מציי, dukyah d'Rava
meheicha eilima mireisha reisha ki miskachshei mitzei, כיון דלא מיזדממי סהדותא כוותייהו
קא קיימא, keivan d'lo mizdammi sahadosa kevaseihu ka kaima, דדינא כוותייהו פסקינן.
d'dina kevaseihu paskinan. So what he's saying is the following: I get
that רבא, Rava, the case, the first case of the רישא reisha,
does sound like there were three כיתות עדים. kitos eidim. Because the
case of the רישא reisha said that the עדים edim that were
found זוממין zomemim said eye and then tooth and the master liked
that testimony. And the only way the master would have liked that
testimony because ultimately they're saying he has to free his slave and
pay for the cost of the tooth, the only way he would
have liked that testimony is if it was preceded by the reverse,
by testimony of tooth and then eye. So in the רישא, reisha
because it says the master likes it, it sounds like there was
an earlier testimony that this testimony is contradicting and therefore it's הכחשה
hachachasha and that shows you that they can still have הזמה after
הכחשה. hachachasha הכחשה תחלת הזמה. hachchasha techilas hazamah. But he's saying, but
I don't get it. Actually, it's not a הכחשה hachashah that neutralized
the testimony because as I indicated before, since the first testimony said
the eye came later and the second testimony of those that were
found זוממין zomemim said the tooth, well, their testimony effectively wins out.
You have a contradiction whether the master is חייב chayiv for the
eye or the tooth, so you're going to do the lesser, you're
going to do the tooth. So you're actually going to do the
פסק psak of the second כת that was found זוממין. zomemin. So
it doesn't prove הכחשה תחלת הזמה. hachchasha techilas hazamah. The הכחשה hachashah
of the first כת did not undermine their testimony. So that's what
he says. Let's read that again.
רישא מכדי מיתכחשי מציי. reisha michadi miskachshei mitzei. In the רישא reisha
the middle כת, the one that said eye and then tooth, you
know, even though they're contradicted, their testimony isn't neutralized. כיון דלא מיזדממי
סהדותא כוותייהו קא קיימא. keivan d'lo mizdammi sahadosa kevaseihu ka kaima. If
they're not made זוממין, zomemin, the ultimately we will follow their testimony.
דדינא כוותייהו פסקינן. d'dina kevaseihu paskinan. We're going to פסקנן paskinan like
them that it's going to say the tooth, not because we know
they're right. But why? דאית בכלל מאה מאתיים. d'is biklal meah masayim.
That included in two hundred is one hundred. The cost of the
tooth is less than the cost of the eye. So if they're
coming second, it's not a הכחשה. hachashah Yes, they are giving different
versions, but... Their פסק psak is going to be followed. So it
doesn't prove whether הכחשה תחילת זומם. hachachasha techilas zomem.
So הילכך קמייהו דקמיכחשי מצעי לא מיכחשי מידי. hilkach kamayehu dekamiskachashey mitzai
lo miskachashey midi. It's the first כת that says the eye came
forward that's being neutralized, not the second one. So I get that
the פשט pshat sounds like there were there was a הכחשה hachashah,
cause it says the master's happy with the testimony, but it's not
an effective הכחשה. hachashah So what's Rava's proof? So אמר ליה רבא,
amar leh Rava, אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said back, as
Rav Ashi said back, רבא סבר מדרישא בשלוש כיתות סיפא נמי בשלוש.
Rava savar mi'dereisha beshalosh kitos seifa nami beshalosh. Ah, you're right. The
רישא reisha is clearly three כיתות kitos for Rava, not like Abaye
tried to say, cause it's clear the master likes the testimony, so
there must be there was an earlier testimony that said otherwise. And
since the רישא reisha. is that there was a previous testimony that
said otherwise, the סיפא seifa is also that way.
Okay. ודייק מדסיפא, vedayek mi'deseifa, and the דיוק diyuk is from סיפא,
seifa כגון, kegon, so what's the case? דאתו בי תרי ואמרי הפיל
לשינו וסימא עינו. de'asu bi trey ve'amri hipil leshino vesimas eino. So
like the רישא reisha that the זוממים zomemim are the middle case.
So first came two and said that it was the tooth and
then the eye. ופסקינן לדינא אפומייהו, upaskinan ledina apumayehu, and then we
פסקן paskin fine pay the eye, that's the גמרא דין. gemara din.
ואתו בי תרי אחריני ואמרי סימא עינו והפיל לשינו, ve'asu bi trey
achrini ve'amri simas eino vehipil leshino,
and then the middle כת middle group comes, and they said it
was the reverse. The tooth was last. So סימא עינו
והפיל לשינו. simas eino vehipil leshino.
דקמכחשי להו להני קמאי. dekamichachashu lehu lehani kamaye. Okay, excuse me, I'm
sorry, I got mixed up which was the first one, which was
the last. I mean I mean okay, the first one is the
one that's going to be זוממים. zomemim Okay, so the first one
said that it was the tooth and the eye, then the second
one said sort of similar order as the first case, then the
second one said eye and then tooth. So in that case we
will follow the second one, tooth is less than eye, so the
first one's testimony that said eye later is actually effectively neutralized. It's
not just contradicted, it's neutralized, we're not going to listen to them,
we're not going to make you pay the cost of the eye,
okay, so it's the same case as the רישא. reisha The first
group said tooth and eye, the second group said eye and tooth.
The difference is that in the סיפא seifa it is the first
group that is found זוממים. zomemim. ונמצאו זוממים קמאי, venimtzu zomemim kamaye,
and the first group is found זוממים, zomemim משלמים דמי עין לרב,
meshalmim demei ayin larav, they have to pay the cost of the
eye, they were lying about the eye being last. Okay, so Rava's
דיוק diyuk is from the fact that the רישא reisha that the
master is happy with the testimony, right, shows that there was an
earlier testimony to the reverse. The סיפא seifa also is that there
was there was a contradictory testimony, and in that case the ones
that are saying eye, their testimony was actually neutralized by those that
said tooth. And nevertheless they can become זוממים. zomemim Okay, which shows
that הכחשה תחילת זומם. hachachasha techilas zomem. ואי סלקא דעתך הכחשה לאו
תחילת זומם היא, ve'isalka deita hachachasha lav techilas zomem hi, and if
הכחשה hakhasha, was not תחילת זומם, techilas zomem,
אמאי משלמים, amai meshalmim, why do they have to pay the cost
of the eye? הא איתכחשו להו מעיקרא, ha'iskachashu lehu mei'ikara, they were
contradicted by those that said tooth. אלא שמע מינה הכחשה תחילת זומם
היא, ela shema mina hachachasha techilas zomem hi, you see that הכחשה
hakhasha is תחילת זומם. techilas zomem. Okay, so Rava says and you
know that the that because there has to be the רישא is
three כיתי עדים, kitay edim, the סיפא seifa is three כיתי עדים,
kitay edim, and in the סיפא seifa the testimony of those that
were found to be זוממים zomemim, was already neutralized as far as
the eye and nevertheless they can be found זוממים, zomemim so you
see that הכחשה תחילת זומם. hachachasha techilas zomem. ואביי אמר לך, ve'Abaye
amar lach, and Abaye will say to you, בשלמא רישא לא סגי
דלא שלוש כיתות. bishlama reisha lo sagi delo shalosh kitos. You're right,
I concede that the beginning first case there had to be three,
before what we said is Abaye said even the first case was
two, but here Abaye is conceding that the first case had to
be three.
שהרי קתני הרב אומר כן. she'harei katana ha'rav omer kein. It says
the master's happy with the testimony. The only way the master's going
to be happy saying he has to free his slave is if
there was another testimony that also said he has to free his
slave but said he had to pay more. So you're right in
the רישא when it says the master's happy clearly there was already
another testimony on the books. אלא סיפא למה לי שלוש כיתות, ela
seifa lama li shalosh kitos, why in the סיפא seifa do you
need three? שהרי עבד אומר כן. she'harei eved omer kein. All it
says is the slave is happy with the testimony when they say
tooth and then eye. עבד כל דהו מימר אמר דניחא ליה דנפיק
לחירות. eved kol de'hu meimar amar denicha lei denafik lecheirus. So the
עבד would be happy you know even if nothing preceded, because tooth
and then eye, that's great, both go free and you get the
eye. So there's no evidence in the סיפא that there is another
group of עדים edim there. So since in the סיפא you know
which is the case where the eye testimony could actually be neutralized,
there's no evidence there was another כת other than the זוממים, zomemim.
then there is no proof that הכחשה תחילת זומם hachachasha techilas zomem
because it could be the זוממים I mean the one that were
the מזימים mazimim actually were the ones that first made them into
זוממים and then also provided the alternative version of what happened. Okay,
so that was pretty complicated but that's the way they debate הכחשה
תחילת זומם. hachachasha techilas zomem. Now we have on this case we
have a just a question about the slave going free. מתקיף לה
רב זירא. maskif lei Rav Zeira. Rav Zeira asked about this whole
case.
אימא סימא עינו נפיק בעינו, הפיל לשינו נפיק בשינו, סימא עינו והפיל
eima simas eino nafik be'eino, hipil leshino nafik beshino, simas eino vehipil
The tooth and the eye, he goes free with one and pays
for the other. Maybe the Torah's saying since he's not free yet,
right, there has to be העמדה בדין. ha'amadah b'din. Maybe the Torah's
saying that the only thing that happens for a tooth or an
eye is going free. So okay, one he went free and the
other he also goes free, you know, but there's no payment.
So אמר אביי, so said Abaye, עליך אמר קרא, alecha amar kra,
תחת עינו, tachas eino, it says you shall send him free in
exchange for his eye, ולא תחת עינו ושינו, v'lo tachas eino v'shino,
not for his eye and his tooth. Only for one of them
he goes free; the other one there has to be some other
form of compensation. Okay, תחת שינו tachas shino in exchange of his
tooth, ולא תחת שינו ועינו, v'lo tachas shino v'eino, but not for
both his tooth and his eye. So only one is sufficient and
necessary and sufficient for going free, so the other one has to
be something else and has to be payment. Okay, אמר רב אידי
בר אבין, Amar Rav Idi bar Avin, אף אנן נמי תנינא, af
anan nami tanina, we also taught about this issue about you
know about הכחשה hakhasha תחילת הזמה. גנב על פי שנים וטבח ומכר
על פיהם ונמצאו זוממין. ganav al pi shnayim v'tavach u'machar al pihem
v'nimtze'u zomemin. Somebody stole based on two witnesses, and they also said
that he sold or
shecheted, and then they were found זוממין. zomemin. משלמין לו את הכל.
meshalmin lo es hakol.
They have to pay this guy everything. They said ראובן Reuven stole
and then shecheted and sold it, and they were זוממין. zomemin. So
now they tried to make him lose out four or five, they
have to pay ראובן Reuven four or five.
Okay now, מאי לאו, mai lav, so presumably it means first they
said he stole, then they said he sold it or shecheted it.
And the הזמה presumably was and presumably, you know, the שחיטה shchitah
was a different day. So they said he stole on Sunday and
he sold it or shecheted it on Monday. And then עדים edim,
came והוזמו על הגנבה, v'huzmu al hagneivah, and they said, no, Sunday
you were with us; you couldn't have seen him steal it. וחזרו
והוזמו על הטביחה, v'chazru v'huzmu al hatvichah, and then they said, and
Monday you were also with us, so you couldn't have seen him
shechet it. Okay, so if that's what happened, וכיון שהוזמו על הגנבה
לגבי טביחה הוי ליה מוכחש. v'keivan shehuzmu al hagneivah lgabi tvichah havvei
leh muchchash. If that's what happened, so as soon as the מזימים
mezimim said you were with us on Sunday, you couldn't have seen
him steal it, it neutralizes the testimony of the שחיטה shchitah because
if he didn't steal it, he didn't shechet it. So now the
testimony of the שחיטה shchitah has been הוכחש, huchash, has been effectively
neutralized. And nevertheless, they he can wind up becoming an עד זומם
ed zomem for the שחיטה shchitah and paying the full four or
five. ותניא משלמין את הכל. v'tanya meshalmin es hakol. So that seems
to prove that even though something gets neutralized and contradicted, it can
end with הזמה. ואי סלקא דעתך הכחשה לאו תחילת הזמה היא, v'ei
salka dachtech hachashah lav techilas hazamah hi, and if you think that
a הכחשה is not the beginning of הזמה, so אטביחה מאי משלמין?
a'tvichah mai meshalmin? Why are you paying for the שחיטה? shchitah? That
was already effectively neutralized. אלא לאו שמע מינה הכחשה תחילת הזמה היא.
ela lav shma mina hachashah techilas hazamah hi. You see that even
when it's contradicted and neutralized, it can still end with הזמה. So
that's his proof. So of course that's just supposing that was the
scenario. אמרי הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שהוזמו אטביחה תחילה. Amri hacha b'mai
askinan kegon shehuzmu a'tvichah techilah. What are we talking about? We're talking
that he was no, you know, you don't have to say it
that way. The מזימים mezimim could say first of all you couldn't
have seen the שחיטה shchitah on Monday, you were with us. That
still would have allowed for the possibility of the גנבה gneivah to
be true. And then they said and you couldn't have seen the
גנבה gneivah on Sunday, you were with us. So there was never
a הכחשה that occurred before the הזמה. Okay. ובפלוגתא, U'v'plugta, this debate
of אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava is a debate of
רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Elazar. עדים שהוכחשו ולבסוף הוזמו.
Edim shehuchashu u'l'vasof huzmu. The witnesses were contradicted and then they were
זוממים. רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר חד אמר נהרגין, Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Elazar
chad amar neheragin, one says they would be killed, assuming they were
testifying about a capital case. וחד אמר אין נהרגין, v'chad amar ein
neheragin, and one says they wouldn't be killed. תיסתיים דרבי אלעזר הוא
דאמר אין נהרגין. Tistayem d'Rabbi Elazar hu d'amar ein neheragin. Let's conclude
that Rabbi Elazar says they would not be killed, meaning הכחשה is
not תחילת הזמה. דאמר רבי אלעזר עדים שהוכחשו בנפש לוקין. D'amar Rabbi
Elazar edim shehuchashu b'nefesh lokin. He said that עדים edim, that testified
about somebody, you know,
who a capital case, could get מלקות. malkus. Now what's the situation
that it's a capital case that you're getting מלקות malkus for being
עדי זוממים? edei zomemim? ואי סלקא דעתך רבי אלעזר הוא דאמר נהרגין,
V'ei salka dachtech Rabbi Elazar hu d'amar neheragin, now if Rabbi Elazar
would say that you are killed, you know, after הכחשה, אמאי לוקין?
amai lokin? You'll never get a case of מלקות. malkus. Either that
won't be sufficient to make them זוממים or you'll make them זוממים
and they'll and they'll you'll kill them. So אמאי לוקין הוי ליה
לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין וכל לאו שניתן לאזהרת
מיתת
בית דין אין לוקין
עליו.
amai lokin havvei leh lav she'nitan l'azharas misas beis din v'chol lav
she'nitan l'azharas
misas beis din ein lokin alav. So what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is, I might have said it a little bit wrong a
second ago, what the גמרא Gemara is saying is that according to
רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, you know, you could imagine a case of
לוקין lokin without making them מזימים, mezimim, and they're לוקין lokin for
for transgressing the prohibition of of bearing false testimony,
so of being given עדות שקר. eidus sheker. So what would be
the case? The case would be they wouldn't be מזימים mezimim but
they were still proved to be lying. Now you're going to ask
how could they be proved lying without מזימים? mezimim? Until now we've
been saying הכחשה neutralizes; you don't know who's telling the truth. Let’s
bracket that for a second, okay? Let’s imagine oh you know what
I’ll tell you what the גמרא Gemara is going to say at
the end. The גמרא’s Gemara going to say at the end בא
הרוג ברגליו. ba harug beraglav. Okay, they said ראובן Reuven killed שמעון
Shimon and then שמעון Shimon walked into בית דין. Beis Din. So
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says they would get even though they’re not
זוממים, they’re going to get מלקות malkus for being עובר over on
the לאו lav of עדות שקר. edus sheker. Okay, but now the
question is one minute. Even though that is מכחיש, makhish, הזמה could
possibly follow. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Let’s read that
again. תיסתיים רבי אליעזר הוא דאמר אין נהרגין. Tistayaim Rabbi Eliezer hu
d’amar ain neheragin. דאמר רבי אליעזר עדים שהוכחשו בנפש לוקין. D’amar Rabbi
Eliezer edim shehukhshu benefesh lokin. If עדים edim, right I misstated it
before. הוכחשו בנפש. Hukhshu benefesh. If עדים edim. were proved contradicted by
a capital case, they’ll get מלקות malkus for
עדות שקר. edus sheker. ואי סלקא דעתך רבי אליעזר הוא דאמר נהרגין,
Ve-isalkadeitach Rabbi Eliezer hu d’amar neheragin, now if רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
was the one who said that they could get killed even after
they’ve been neutralized and contradicted, אמאי לוקין, amai lokin, why would they
get מלקות malkus for עדות שקר? edus sheker? הוי ליה לאו שניתן
לאזהרת מיתת בית דין. Havay lay lav she-nitan le-azharas misas beis din.
Yes, they would have transgressed the prohibition of עדות שקר edus sheker
but it is a transgression you don't get מלקות malkus on something
that could lead to being חייב מיתת בית דין. chayav misas beis
din. Okay, וכל לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין, vechol lav she-nitan
le-azharas misas beis din, since this could turn into מיתת בית דין.
misas beis din. Why? Because after the הכחשה, if עדים מזימים edim
mazimim would come, they would be חייב מיתה. chayav misa. So if
this is a process that could end in מיתת בית דין, misas
beis din, they can’t get מלקות. malkus. אין לוקין וכל לאו שניתן
לאזהרת מיתת בית דין, Ain lokin vechol lav she-nitan le-azharas misas beis
din, any לאו lav that is given to be the warning to
get
מיתה, misa, you don’t get
מלקות. malkus. אלא לאו שמע מינה רבי אליעזר הוא דאמר אין נהרגין.
Ela lav she-mina Rabbi Eliezer hu d’amar ain neheragin. It must be
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says you would not kill them. תיסתיים, Tistayaim,
then that is a good proof. Okay, so again because רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says that if they’re proven to be lying without being
זוממים they get מלקות malkus for עדות שקר, edus sheker, it must
mean that there is not a possible end of the road here
that will end with them getting killed. That the הכחשה can’t complete
with becoming זוממים. Because if a possible end of the road could
lead to them getting killed, then we would פסקן paskin then there
would no way they could get מלקות malkus because it would be
a לאו שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין. lav she-nitan le-azharas misas beis
din. And now the גמרא Gemara. says לוקין? Lokin? תרי ותרי נינהו.
Trei ve-trei ninhu. מאי חזית דסמכת אהני סמוך אהני? Mai chazis she-samacht
a-hani samach a-hani? If they're contradicted,
why do you think that they're lying? You don't know who to
believe, it's two against two. אמר אביי בבא הרוג ברגליו, Amar Abaye
b’ba harug beraglav, שמעון Shimon who was said to be the murder
victim he walked into בית דין Beis Din totally happy and healthy.
So clearly they were lying. Now how do you know they weren't
mistaken with the identity or whatever, but okay that would be enough
and they would get מלקות malkus for עדות שקר. edus sheker. תוספות
Tosfos by the way asks that why is this considered like לאו
שניתן לאזהרת מיתת בית דין. lav she-nitan le-azharas misas beis din. Normally
it doesn't matter that this act could get you מיתת בית דין,
misas beis din, it means that there's a way that this לאו
lav could be used to punish somebody for מיתת בית דין. misas
beis din. So why here's it important that the this process end
with מיתת בית דין? misas beis din? And he says because we
know explicitly based on a פסוק posuk that you can get מלקות
malkus for עדות שקר. edus sheker. So that we know. So once
it's possible to get מלקות malkus for עדות שקר, edus sheker, we
know that the fact that עדות שקר edus sheker can sometimes lead
to מיתת בית דין misas beis din is not enough to get
you off the hook for מלקות. malkus. But if the very testimony
itself could lead to מיתת בית דין, misas beis din, then there's
no way you could be getting מלקות malkus for it. Okay, and
therefore it must be for רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer once there's הכחשה
it cannot end with הזמה. Let's start the next משנה. Mishnah. גנב
על פי שנים וטבח ומכר על פי אחד, Ganav al pi shenayim
ve-tavach u-machar al pi echad, somebody stole based on two witnesses and
then שחט shekhted or sold it based on only one witness, או
על פי עצמו, o al pi atzmo, or his own testimony, משלם
תשלומי כפל ואינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. meshalem tashlumei khefel ve-eino meshalem
tashlumei arba ve-chamishah. You don't pay four or five, this is a
קנס knas and therefore you're not חייב chayav by your own testimony
and you need two witnesses. גנב וטבח בשבת גנב וטבח לעבודה זרה.
Ganav ve-tavach be-shabbos ganav ve-tavach le-avodah zarah. Now let's say he stole
and שחט shekhted on שבת Shabbos or stole and he שחט shekhted
for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. The emphasis being שחיטה shekhting on שבת,
Shabbos, שחיטה shekhting for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Both of those things
are חייב מיתה. chayav misa. גנב משל אביו ומת אביו ואחר כך
טבח ומכר. Ganav mi-shel aviv ve-meis aviv ve-achar kach tavach u-machar. If
he stole from his father and then his father died and then
he שחט shekhted and sold it. So when he sold it he
already inherited it from his father, so he was selling something that
was already his. גנב והקדיש Ganav ve-hikdish if he stole and was
sanctified it, ואחר כך טבח ומכר ve-achar kach tavach u-machar and then
he sold it and then he slaughtered it or sold it, משלם
תשלומי כפל ואינו משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה. meshalem tashlumei khefel ve-eino meshalem
tashlumei arba ve-chamishah. You don't pay four or five, so why? Because
you don't pay if it already belongs to הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, so
when you inherited it if guy inherits it because his father died
he doesn't pay it's already his. When he's מקדיש makdish it he
doesn't pay four or five because there's no חיוב chiyuv on something
that's הקדש. hekdesh. How about the case of שחיטה shekhting on שבת
Shabbos and שחיטה shekhting for עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? So that's more
of a קים ליה בדרבה מיניה kim lay b'deraba minei doing an
act that's חייב מיתה chayav misa overrides the cost of payment the
obligation of payment we'll see more about that in the גמרא. Gemara.
רבי שמעון אומר קדשים שחייב באחריותם משלם תשלומי ארבעה וחמישה שאין חייב
באחריותם פטור. Rabbi Shimon omer kodashim she-chayav be-achrayusam meshalem tashlumei arba ve-chamishah
she-ein chayav be-achrayusam patur. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says I distinguish between
whether you are liable to replace it or not a certain קרבן
korban that you have to replace is still considered yours so then
you are חייב chayav four and five only. If you don't have
to replace it, is it not considered yours and you're exempt? We'll
see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, we're going to take
these one by one. First, we're going to look at this case
about your own testimony or the testimony of an עד אחד. ed
echad. So, up גמרא. Gemara על פי עד אחד פשיטא, Al pi
ed echad peshita, obviously, there's no obligation, this is a קנס. knas.
הא קמשמע לן על פי עצמו דומיא דעל פי עד אחד. Ha
kamashma lan al pi atzmo dumya d'al pi ed echad. No, this
is teaching you that your own testimony is not different, you know,
than one עד. ed, What does that mean? מה על פי עד
אחד כי אתי עד אחד מצטרף בהדיה מחייב, Mah al pi ed
echad ki atei ed echad mistaraf bahadei mechayev, the same way when
it's one עד, that doesn't get you off the hook, it just
means it's not sufficient. And if there would become two עדים, edim
you would be חייב. chayav. So, so, על פי עצמו נמי, al
pi atzmo nami, so your own testimony as well, כי אתו עדים
מחייב, ki atu edim mechayev, it doesn't get you off the hook,
it just means it's not sufficient. But if עדים edim would come
afterwards, you would be חייב. chayav. ולאפוקי מדרב הונא אמר רב, Ulefukei
merav huna amar rav, to this reading gets you out, it you
know, rejects the or contradicts the position of רב הונא אמר רב
Rav Huna amar Rav דאמר רב הונא אמר רב מודה בקנס ואחר
כך באו עדים פטור. damar Rav Huna amar Rav modeh beknas ve'achar
kach ba'u edim patur. That רב הונא Rav Huna says in the
name of רב, Rav, if somebody agrees for a קנס knas and
then עדים edim come, you are פטור, patur, meaning mean meaning this
is the question of what happens when you admit for something that's
a קנס. knas. Is it that then it's like a type of
a תשובה teshuvah and a קנס knas was to punish you? So
therefore, the fact that you admitted it is enough to actually exempt
you from payment, even if witnesses come afterwards, does your admission exempt
you or is your admission just not sufficient to obligate you? Okay,
so that's a very central question about what מודה בקנס modeh beknas
does. And now we're going to focus on that. גופא. Gufa. אמר
רב הונא אמר רב מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים פטור.
Amar Rav Huna amar Rav modeh beknas ve'achar
kach ba'u edim patur. So even though we said that was the
משנה Mishnah suggested against this position, we're now going to see a
number of, you know, אמוראים Amoraim that agree with it, that actually
admitting to a קנס knas actually exempts you. איתיביה רב חסדא לרב
הונא. Eiseivah Rav Chisda leRav Huna. רב חסדא Rav Chisda challenged רב
הונא. Rav Huna. מעשה ברבן גמליאל שסימא את עין טבי עבדו והיה
שמח שמחה גדולה. Maiseh beRabban Gamliel shesimah es ein Tevi avdo vehaya
sameach simchah gedolah. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel blinded the eye of טבי,
Tevi, his servant, who he was a very dear to him, and
he said you know טבי כשר הוא Tevi kasher hu and, you
know, many stories in the משנה Mishnah about how much respect he
held טבי Tevi in, not clear how he blinded his eye. Was
he hitting his slave that was so beloved to him? Was it
an accident? But anyway, he was very joyous. Why? Because now טבי
Tevi was going to be able to go free, and he couldn't
have freed him just, you know, unilaterally, because there's an understanding that
there's a מצות עשה mitzvas asei not to free your slave. So
מצאו לרבי יהושע, matzo leRabbi Yehoshua, he he bumped into רבי יהושע,
Rabbi Yehoshua, אמר לו אי אתה יודע שטבי עבדי יצא לחירות. amar
lo ee atah yodeia sheTevi avdi yatza lecherus. Hey, רבי יהושע, Rabbi
Yehoshua, it's so amazing, did you hear the great news? My slave
טבי Tevi is going to be free. I mean, he lost his
eye, but he's going to be free. אמר לו למה, Amar lo
lamah, he said why? אמר לו שסימיתי את עינו, Amar lo shesimiti
es eino, cause I knocked out his eye. אמר לו אין בדבריך
כלום, Amar lo ein bidvarecha kelum, sorry, in,
you know, you're not it's not going to happen, שכבר אין לו
עדים, shekvar ein lo edim, because there are no witnesses.
So he said, so the problem was that there wasn't enough to
obligate him. אין
לו עדים. Ein lo edim. הא יש לו עדים, Ha yesh lo
edim, but if there were witnesses, חייב, chayav, then he would go
free, even though רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel already admitted to it. ושמעינן
מינה מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים מחייב, Vishmaninah minei modeh beknas
ve'achar kach ba'u edim mechayev, you see that even though if somebody
admits to a קנס knas and then עדים come, you're חייב. chayav.
A קנס knas admitting doesn't exempt you, it just doesn't obligate you.
So רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, he admitted it, and the implication was
if there's going to be עדים, you're still going to be חייב.
chayav. So you see that admitting does not exempt, it just does
not obligate. So אמר ליה, amar lei, so רב הונא Rav Huna
said back, שאני רבן גמליאל דלא בפני בית דין אודי. shani Rabban
Gamliel delo bifnei beis din hoda'ei. No, that didn't count, because, you
know, even though, because רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was not testifying to
a בית דין. beis din. He just said to his friend רבי
יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, that's not a testimony that counts as a הודאה
hoda'ah to exempt you. A הודאה hoda'ah that would exempt you would
be a coming to בית דין beis din and admit it. So
the גמרא Gemara says ורבי יהושע אב בית דין הוה, veRabbi Yehoshua
av beis din havah, but רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was an אב
בית דין, av beis din, so he was telling him to a
בית דין. beis din. Now of course you could say, just because
somebody happens to be an אב בית דין av beis din doesn't
mean when you find him in the supermarket that you're testifying in
a בית דין, beis din, which is what the גמרא Gemara says,
top of ע"ה עמוד א'. Ayin Hei Amud Aleph. שלא בבית דין
הוה קאי. Shelo beveis din havah kai. He wasn't in a בית
דין. beis din. Who cares that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua was an
אב בית דין? av beis din? It still wasn't a testimony in
a בית דין. beis din. But I will still assert that if
it was a testimony in a בית דין, beis din, it would
exempt him, even if witnesses would come afterwards. והתניא, Vehatanya, but wait,
we have another ברייתא, Baraita different version of the story. אמר לו
אין בדבריך כלום שכבר הודית. Amar lo ein bidvarecha kelum shekvar hodisa.
He said that, you know, sorry buddy, רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, he's
not going to go free because you already admitted. So your admission
is going to is going to prevent him from going free. So
that really sounds like a strong point that at least that version
of the ברייתא Baraita is a strong support of רב הונא אמר
רב. Rav Huna amar Rav. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו
תנאי, mai lav tanna'ei, it must be a debate of תנאים. tanna'im.
האי תנא דאמר שכבר אין לך עדים, Hai tanna d'amar shekvar ein
lecha edim, the one that said the problem was the absence of
עדים, סבר מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים מחייב savar modeh beknas
ve'achar kach ba'u edim mechayev sounds like a הודאה hoda'ah followed Following
עדים, you would be חייב. chayav. The problem was absence of עדים.
והאי תנא דאמר שכבר הודית, v'hai tanna d'amar she'kvar hodaita, and the
תנא tanna that says, "Oh, look, you testified, now he won't go
free, now you're exempt," סבר מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים פטור.
savar modeh b'knas v'achar kach ba'u edim patur. You said that once
you admit, even if עדים were to come, you would remain exempt.
Now, it certainly is true that the second ברייתא Baraita makes that
clear. The second ברייתא Baraita says, you've already admitted, so now he
can't go free. That clearly holds like אמר רב הונא אמר רב
Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav that מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים
פטור, modeh b'knas v'achar kach ba'u edim patur, that your הודאה hoda'ah
exempts you. The first one that said that if עדים were to
come you'd be חייב chayav does not necessarily hold the opposite position.
גמרא says, "לא דכולי עלמא מודה בקנס ואחר כך באו עדים פטור."
lo de'chuli alma modeh b'knas v'achar kach ba'u edim patur. I can
say everybody agrees that your admission exempts you. ובהא קמיפלגי. uv'ha ka'miflegi.
This is the debate. האי תנא דאמר שכבר אין לך עדים hai
tanna d'amar she'kvar ein lecha edim סבר חוץ לבית דין הוה, savar
chutz l'beis din hava, like we said before. The one that says
that there were no עדים said there was not a legitimate admission,
it wasn't in the presence of a בית דין. Beis Din. והאי
תנא דאמר שכבר הודית, v'hai tanna d'amar she'kvar hodaita, the one that
says that the הודאה hoda'ah exempted you here, סבר בבית דין הוה,
savar b'veis din hava, it was a בית דין. Beis Din. So
bottom line is our משנה Mishnah the דיוק diyuk is against אמר
רב הונא אמר רב Amar Rav Huna Amar Rav that your admission
does not exempt you. Here we have a ברייתא Baraita שכבר הודית
she'kvar hodaita that clearly makes it clear that your admission did exempt
you. And the ברייתא שאין לך עדים she'ein lecha edim can go
either way. The ברייתא שאין לך עדים she'ein lecha edim could either
show that your admission does not exempt you, or could understand your
admission exempts you, but this was not an actual admission in front
of a בית דין. Beis Din. Okay, we will stop here.